What is algorithm in computer programming terms, an algorithm is a set of well-defined instructions
to solve a particular problem.
It takes a set of input and produces a desired output.
So an algorithm is the step by step unambiguous instructions to solve a given problem.
An example for an algorithm like adding two numbers in order to add two numbers, you should take two
numbers.
Input.
Okay, so we have number one, we have a valuable call, number one and we have entered the user entered
number four.
So Ford is stored inside.
One variable and other variable is listening for that user input, and the user input is 70.
So 70 is and is like stored inside numb to variable.
Ad numbers using the plus operator and memory and the spew and do this in their arithmetic and logical
unit so that this would result in giving us in the resolved a new valuable code sample, which is 74.
So we have stored 74 inside the some value.
Another example of algorithms.
To find the largest number among three numbers, the first step in computer engineering or computer
science and programming.
You need to start the program.
Non net declare variables A B and three and C, so we have three variables.
Number one, two and three.
Read the variables ABC or number one to number three.
So a would be result in one four to one, which the user input B or numb to would be the input of the
user, which is seventy and three number three, or C is 12.
These are the reading of the BI, so we have created declared variables we have instantiate in sheet
and instantiate the data inside them and stored the data that entered by the user inside them.
Now we need to make that comparison, so.
If no one greater than NUM do and this is the case here, so no one is greater than do we took no one
as the biggest and the bigger between number one and two.
OK, then we are going to compare number one with number three, since no one is greater number.
Number two.
So no need to compare number two with the number three.
We take number one and compare it with three.
And since no one is greater than number three, so number one is the greatest among the three given
inputs A, B, C or none one, two and three.
OK.
There is another way.
And another thing that we should consider maybe the first number or number one is not greater than two.
So there is an L condition.
So if a greater, then B and this is our case.
So it works fine and we need and we should consider all the cases we need to cover all the cases inside
a good algorithm in order not to have bugs or errors during running the product.
So if B greater than C or sorry, if b greater than A, then proceed b greater than C, then display
B is the largest otherwise c it the greatest number and step number five step stop the program.
Let's take an algorithm three, find the root of the quadratic equation a x squared plus b x plus C
equal to zero.
In order to solve like this example, we should make declared three variables A, B and C. We store
a as one because it's multiplied by one.
For example, the user enter one B storing it inside inside it to the user.
Enter to and c the user entered one and stored inside c.
Now we need to declare another variable called determinant.
This determinant is calculated by b squared minus four AC.
This is the delta or the determinant.
So the determinant of these is if this equation, the user entered a as one, B S2 and C as one.
The determinant of this would be equal to zero.
This result?
Or that determinant will determine the roots of our quadratic equation.
Either they are real or they are imaginary.
So if the greater than or equal to zero, there are two worlds two real roots.
Or if the less than zero, we will see the complex rules.
So if they're greater than zero or or equal to zero, then create two other variables are one and or
two.
OK, we have a B and C D capital and R1 and R2 till now R1 and Arta are representing the roots of this
equation.
So R1 is calculated by minus B plus radical B squared minus four AC over to A.
And in this case is equal to minus one, and R2 is calculated by minus B minus radical B squared minus
40 c over to a.
And this this example would result in R1 equal R2, which is the double routes.
One determinant is equal to zero.
If decorators and zero, then we have two distinct routes.
Now, if they're less than zero, there is a real part which is calculated by minus B over to a an imaginary
part.
Radical B squared minus four AC over to a.
OK, so we need now to calculate the routes by putting the real part.
Plus, J Times IP and R2 is our real part, minus J Times IP.
In this case, we need to create two variables R1 and R2.
And we calculate the real part and the imaginary part and multiply them by Jane.
So this complexity in a small quadratic equation.
So how to solve this equation?
Learned later on how to write the codes responsible for making this algorithm working on many coding
languages.
Now to see the algorithms in our daily lives.
Consider a teacher, so consider a teacher need to sort the papers of and for the students in alphabetical
order.
This type of desk is similar to the function of a sorting algorithm like a bucket sort.
And we will learn about this sorting algorithms later on through a discourse.
By looking at only the first letter of the first name, you can remove a lot of unnecessary information
like this.
The student last name, the student name and the student age or the student class or what and the date
of the of the exam.
So we need the first letter of the first name in order to sort them alphabetically.
Algorithms in our daily life also.
So think about arrangement of leader board game.
And you need an algorithm like helping you to find the smaller, all or largest number in a list of
thousands of number.
So you need an algorithm to find the correct number and the correct score, or you need to keep track
of the highest score in the video game.
Or you need to find out which seats on a train or plane are occupied.
Or finding or listing results from search engines like Google.
And providing the instructions that tell you how to get from one location to another with the shortest
way using Google Maps, these algorithms also we are going to learn more about them through this course.